<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Orderly and plaine narration of the beginnings and causes of this warre also a conscientious resolution against the warre on the Parlaiments side.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27639</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12095034</idno>
  <idno type="VID">196782</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240928153</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12095034</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 196782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 237:E54, no 3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Orderly and plaine narration of the beginnings and causes of this warre also a conscientious resolution against the warre on the Parlaiments side.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Leonard Lichfield]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:196782:1"/>
            <p>An orderly and plaine NARRATION Of the Beginnings and Causes of this WARRE. Also A conscientious Resolution against the WARRE on the PARLIAMENTS side.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 24.21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My son, feare thou the Lord, and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
               <p>For their calamity shall rise sodainly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:196782:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:196782:2"/>
            <head>An orderly and plaine Narration of the Beginnings and Causes of this Warre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Religion by Law established in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ever since the first Reformation, hath been opposed doubly; by the Papists, and by the Discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narians: and from these have proceeded our late, and present Warres in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In King <hi>Edward's</hi> dayes, Master <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Epistle to the Lord Protectour, writeth thus, <hi>Sir, I heare that there are two sorts of seditious men amongst you, who lift up the head against the King and the State of the Kingdome. The one are a sort of brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke men, who promote their Sedition under the name of the Gospell; the others are so hardened in the Superstitions of Antichrist, that they cannot endure a revulsion of them. And both these sorts of men must be restrained by the revenging sword, which the Lord hath put into thine hand: since they rise up not onely against the King, but against God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, who hath placed the King in his Royall Throne, and made thee Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour of his Person, and his Royall Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, the Disciplinarians became more violent, and declared openly, that for the great Cause, the holy Cause (so they called the Presbytery) they would never leave suing, though there should be a thousand Parliaments, untill they obtain it, or bring the Lord in vengeance and blood upon the State for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gibson</hi> threatned King <hi>James,</hi> that as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> He should be root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and conclude his Race, if He maintained Bishops.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:196782:3"/>
            <p>And all the world sees, how the rage and fury of these men hath broke out into open force, and actuall Warre, in King <hi>Charles</hi> his time.</p>
            <p>Now I conceive this Faction hath encreased from time to time
<list>
                  <item>1. By reason the Lawes against them have not been put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that especially of the 35. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. whereby it is enacted, that all those who would not be present at Divine Service, and should hold Conventicles, and deny the Queenes Supremacy in Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall matters should abjure the Land, otherwise to suffer as Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons; and having abjured the Land, and returning without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, then likewise to suffer as Felons.</item>
                  <item>2. By meanes of the City of <hi>London,</hi> (the Nest and Seminary of the seditious Faction) and by reason of its universall Trade through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdome, with its Commodities conveying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving this civill contagion to all our Cities and Corporations, and thereby poysoning whole Counties.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And the Power of this Faction is advanced at this day by reason of the populousnesse and wealth of the City of <hi>London,</hi> (ambitious for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth to be a free State) and by the compliance of divers Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both Houses with them, which in former Parliaments they could never obtain: and under the venerable name of Parliament, and by the force and prevalency of this Faction have things been carried on, and this present Warre both begun and continued; whilest the Parliament serves their turne to root out Episcopacy, and they serve the Parliaments turne to overthrow Monarchy.</p>
            <p>When the Lords at <hi>Yorke</hi> petitioned his Majesty to call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Scene was laid at <hi>London,</hi> doubtlesse in reference to the Designe: and in pursuance thereof (when the Parliament was called) they used the greatest industry that may be to bring in persons of their Faction into the House of Commons; and they admitted, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived such (of their Faction) who were neither lawfully chosen, nor returned by their Countrey; and they put, and kept out others, whose opinions they liked not. And not long after they were setled in Parliament, out of a sense of the grievances of the Kingdome, and of the late oppressions of the Subject (as was pretended) and out of a zeale against the Authours thereof and the Actors therein, they passe severall Votes against all such Lords as had concurred in such an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:196782:3"/>at the Councell-Table, or such a Censure in the Stat Chamber; and against all Lords-Lieutenants, and their Deputies, who had raised Coat and Conduct-money: and all Sheriffes who had levied Ship-money; and all Lords, and others, who had been concerned in any Monopoly, or illegall Patent. But what is the aime of their terrible Votes? Not Justice: for they proceed not against those Offenders; but compilance, to awe not a small number of the Members of both Houses, and to captivate them and their Votes, and to governe them in the managing of their Designe for the altering of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church and State.</p>
            <p>Which alterations they first attempted in a Parliamentary way; and so (in <hi>May</hi> 1641) a Bill was tendred in the House of Commons for the utter abolition of Bishops out of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and for Extirpation of Deanes and Chapters, and this was in debate ten weekes, but it passed not. Likewise Sir <hi>Arthur Hasterigge</hi> brought a Bill into the House of Commons (<hi>Octob.</hi> 1641. which was before the King's comming to the House, or the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi>) to place a Generall at Land, and an Admirall at Sea, by Act of Parliament, with uncontrollable power and authority over the lives and fortunes of all his Majesties Subjects (the matter of which Bill, to shew their Designe, is since digested into their Generals Commission, and their Ordinance to the Earle of <hi>Warwicke.</hi>) And this Bill was cast out of the House with indignation; and it was moved, that it should be burnt by the hand of the common Hangman.</p>
            <p>Lastly, (in <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1641.) there was a long debate in the House of Commons concerning the Book of Common Prayer, and much more the <hi>major</hi> part voted for it.</p>
            <p>After they saw that they could not compasse their Designe upon free debating and voting in a Parliamentary way, they resolve to drive it on otherwise: and under pretence of advancing the ordinance of Preaching, and of promoting the salvation of the simple and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people, they setup Lecturers in every Parish, such as might be furious promoters of their dangerous Innovations; and they cherish such men as boldly and seditiously preach against the Government of the Church, the Book of Common Prayer, and his Majesties Kingly and lawfull Power, and against his very Person; and many of them are recommended to Parishes by Letters, and by Orders. Likewise
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:196782:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:196782:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:196782:5"/>licence is given to lewd and seditious Pamphlets, which despised the Government both of Church and State, and laid imputations and scornes on his Majesties Person Office, and Government, (and this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so was the chiefe argument of their Remonstrance, <hi>Dec.</hi> 15. 1641.) yea and bookes against the Book of Common Prayer and the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lawes of the Land are suffered without reprehension to be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And when by these seditious practices, and Pamphlets, and by that Remonstrance, they had brought the people into dislike of the present Government of the Kingdome, and had gained them to themselves; upon pretence of a Thorough-Reformation intended to be wrought by them, they apply themselves to their Designe again; and now they go in a mixt way, by the Parliament, and the People; and they betake themselves to Tumults, about the latter end of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> so that when any thing in agitation was likely to be carried against them, they send for multitudes, especially of those seditious and factious People, in and about <hi>London,</hi> who misuse the severall Members of both Houses whom they were informed favoured not their ends, proclaiming the names of severall of the Peeres as evill and rotten-hearted Lords, and assaulting, and evill entreating some of the Members of the House of Commons, even at the doore of that House; whereupon the House of Peeres twice very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desired the House of Commons, that they would for the Dignity of Parliament joyne with them in a Declaration for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing such Tumults; but instead thereof, Speeches were made in justification of them: and afterwards when the Lords by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Judges had given Order to the Justices of Peace, and other Officers about <hi>Westminster,</hi> to endeavour the suppressing of those Tumults, one of the Iustices for doing his duty therein was sent to the Tower.</p>
            <p>At last, his Majesty being sensible of his own and the Parliaments great disturbance by those Tumults, sent a Message to the Lord Maior (<hi>Decemb.</hi> 31.) requiring him for the time to come to take speciall care for the preventing the like Tumults, as farre as in him lay.</p>
            <p>And when none of these courses could prevaile, but the People grew more and more outragious and insolent, his Majesty (well
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:196782:5"/>knowing who they were that first raised and invited the tumultuous people to <hi>Westminster,</hi> and what was their Designe thereby) exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth Articles of High Treason against the Lord <hi>Kymbolton</hi> (now Earle of <hi>Manchester</hi>) and against the Five Members, Master <hi>Pym,</hi> M. <hi>Hampden,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerigge,</hi> and M. <hi>Strood.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That they have traiterously endeavoured to subvert the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes and Government of this Kingdome, and to deprive the King of his Regall Power, and to place in Subjects an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall Power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That they have endeavoured by many false aspersions upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and upon his Government, to alienate the affections of his People, and to make his Majesty odious to them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That they have endeavoured to draw his Majesties late Army to disobedience to his Commands, and to side with them in their traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Designes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That they have traiterously invited and encouraged a Forraigne Power to invade his Majesties Kingdome of</hi> England.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>That they have traiterously endeavoured to subvert the Rights and very Beings of Parliaments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>That for compleating their traiterous Designes, they have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure as farre as in them lay, by force and terrour to compell the Parliament to joyne with them in their traiterous Designes, and to that end have actually raised and countenanced Tumults against the King and Parliament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>That they have traiterously conspired to leavy, and actually have leavied Warre against the King.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And in this case of Treason, his Majesty might have apprehended those persons by an Ordinary Minister of Iustice (according to that Maxime in the Law, that in case of Treason, Felony, and Breach of Peace, Priviledge of Parliament doth not extend, is of no signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.)</p>
            <p>But to shew his correspondence with the two Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Majesty chose rather to command the Attourney Generall to acquaint the House of Peeres with his Charge against the Lord <hi>Kymbolton,</hi> and his intention to proceed accordingly. And to send a Sergeant at Armes to the House of Commons to acquaint them, that his Majesty did accuse and intend to prosecute the Five Members
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:196782:6"/>for High Treason, and did require that their persons might be secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in custody.</p>
            <p>That same day (<hi>viz. Ian.</hi> 4.) the House of Commons made an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and published it, that if any person shall arrest those Members, or any other, (without Order from that House) the parties arrested might stand upon their Guard and make resistance, and others might, and ought to assist them, according to the Protestation taken to defend the Priviledges of Parliament, 5. <hi>May</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>Vpon this Order, the King is forced to go in Person to the House of Commons to demand those Members; and He is no sooner gone thence, but the House adjourned it selfe; and instead of any applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to informe his Majesties judgement wherein He had erred, and how He was to proceed, both the Houses adjourned themselves to <hi>Guild hall,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Grocers-hall;</hi> and the Persons accused remove themselves into the City, as to a Sanctuary: and the Common Councell of <hi>London</hi> (altered by undue practises about <hi>Christmas</hi> last) place unusuall Watches and Guards in the City under the Command of Sergeant Major Generall <hi>Skippon,</hi> (as is pretended) for the safety of the City, and the protection of the Members; not so onely, but <hi>Ian.</hi> 11. the Trained Bands of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster</hi> guard those accused Members from their residence in the City to <hi>Westminster,</hi> in an hostile and warlike manner; and neare one hundred Lighters and Long-boates were set out by water, laden with Sacres, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Pieces, and other Ammunition, dressed up with mast-clothes, and streamers, as ready to fight; and in this Array the Mariners by water, and the Souldiers by Land, as they passed by <hi>Whitehall,</hi> asked, what was become of the King? where was He?</p>
            <p>To compose these Distempers, his Majesty makes this proposition to both Houses of Parliament <hi>Ian.</hi> 20. that they will with all speed fall into a serious consideration of all those particulars which they held necessary, as well for the upholding and maintaining of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties just and Regall Authority, and for setling of his Revenue; as for the present and future establishment of their Priviledges, the free and quiet enjoying of their estates and fortunes, the liberty of their persons, the security of the true Religion now professed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the setling of Ceremonies in such a manner as may take away all just offence: all which when they shall present
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:196782:6"/>unto his Majesty, digested into one Body, he promiseth (to shew how farre he hath been from intending or designing any of those things which the too great Feares and Iealousies of some persons seem to apprehend) not onely to equall, but also to exceed the greatest Examples of the most indulgent Princes in their Acts of Grace and Favour to their people.</p>
            <p>But before they take into consideration this Message (having now found out a meanes to shelter themselves, how traiterous soever, under the pretended Priviledge of Parliament, and to promote their Designe by the people under colour of maintaining the power of the Priviledge of Parliament, the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster</hi> having already engaged themselves on their behalfe, and the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Counties by their severall Petitions having declared their good affections toward them) maugre his Majesties Accusation of High Treason, they take courage and revive the matter of the Bill exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerigge</hi> in <hi>October</hi> last, for transferring all his Majesties power into other hands. And they put a Garrison into the Town of <hi>Hull,</hi> and appoint Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> the Governour of it, and they possesse themselves of his Majesties Magazine there, and manage and dispose it as they please. And <hi>Ian.</hi> 27. the House of Commons, as is pretended, to enable them with security to discharge their duty about that Message, petitioned his Majesty, that the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and the principall Forts and the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome might be put into the hands of such persons as should be recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them: and the Lords having refused to joyne with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in that Petition, multitudes of poore people in and about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> did therefore petition the House of Commons, <hi>Ian.</hi> 31. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of a malignant party in the Lords House (those who would not joyne with them in the <hi>Militia</hi>-businesse) and desiring that they be made manifest unto them, declaring that they, would lay hold on the next opportunity, to remove those Disturbera of their peace. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that day Master <hi>Hollis</hi> made a Speech to the Lords, enforcing the petition at a Conference with the House of Commons; whereupon divers Lords being discontented went away; and so the <hi>Militia</hi> was carried in the Lords House (or rather they shuffled themselves into the <hi>Militia</hi>) being at least twice before rejected by double their number who consented to it, when there was no popish Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:196782:7"/>and twelve Bishops in the Tower: and since that time they have been able to carry any thing, and upon the matter, the resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the House of Commons hath been wholly guided by those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who had given so plain evidence that they had the multitude at their command, and hath wholly guided that of the House of Peeres, who with little debate, or dispute, have, for the most part, submitted to whatsoever hath been brought to them.</p>
            <p>Two dayes after <hi>viz. Febr.</hi> 2. the Lords and Commons petition the King that he would be pleased forthwith to put the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and all other Forts, and the whole <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome, into the hands of such persons as should be recommended to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty by both Houses of Parliament; that, as is pretended, they may se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely prosecute his Majesties gracious Message, as before, but indeed that they may more securely prosecute their Designe. And <hi>Febr.</hi> 12. they offer to his Majesty a List of the names of those men which were thought fit to be intrusted with the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Febr.</hi> 16. they renew their Petition concerning the <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also <hi>Febr.</hi> 25. they offer unto him the Ordinance of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>March</hi> 1. they petition him again concerning the <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And lastly, they mention the businesse of the <hi>Militia</hi> in their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to his Majesty, <hi>March</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>Now to these severall Petitions, and to their Ordinance, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty returnes severall Answers, the summe whereof is this.</p>
            <p>First, concerning their Feares and Iealousies, which seem to be the ground of their Petitions and Ordinance;</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1. He sayes, <hi>that if they will acquaint Him with the particular grounds of their Doubts and Feares, He will apply Remedies proportionable to those Feares. Ian.</hi> 27</item>
               <item n="2">2. <hi>He con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ures them, that they would not be transported by Iealousies and Apprehensions of possible Dangers, to put themselves or his Maiesty into reall and present inconveniences. Ian.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item n="3">3. He promiseth in this case <hi>to deny them nothing but what would alter the Fundamentall Lawes of the Land, and nourish a greater and more destructive Iealousie between the Crown and the Subiect, than any of those which would seem to be taken away by such a satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ian.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item n="4">4. He hopes, <hi>that their Feares and Iealousies will hereafter be continued
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:196782:7"/>onely with reference to his Majesties Rights and Honour. Febr.</hi> 24.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, concerning the preamble to the Ordinance, which mentions a most dangerous and desperate Designe of late upon the House of Commons, voted to be an effect of the bloody Counsels of Papists, and others ill affected, whereby doubtlesse is meant his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties comming in Person to the House of Commons. <hi>Jan.</hi> 4.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1. His Majesty declares, and calls Almighty God to witnesse, that <hi>He had no other Designe upon that House, or any Member of it, than to require, as He did, the persons of those five Gentlemen He had the day before accused of High Treason, and to declare that He meant to proceed against them legally, and speedily. Feb.</hi> 28.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And if Marques <hi>Hamilton</hi> had any hand in the Kings going to the House, it is not improbable but that the motion might come originally from themselves, thereby to entrap his Majesty, and to picke a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with Him, and wrest the <hi>Militia</hi> from Him.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="2">2. Concerning Papists, his Majesty signified by a Message to both Houses of Parliament. <hi>Febr.</hi> 14.</item>
            </list>
            <p>First, that <hi>He will by Proclamation require that all Statutes made concerning Recusants, be with all care, diligence and severity put in execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that <hi>He will give present order, if it shall be held fit by both Houses, that a Proclamation issue, to require all Romish Priests within twenty dayes to depart the Kingdome. And if any shall be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended after that time, that He will grant no pardon to any such without consent of his Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also his Majesty did set forth a Proclamation for putting the Lawes against Papists in execution. <hi>March</hi> 16.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="3">3. <hi>For the persons nominated to be Lieutenants of the severall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, his Majesty is contented to allow that recommendation, onely concerning the City of</hi> London, <hi>and such other Corporations as by ancient Charters have granted unto them the power of the</hi> Militia, <hi>his Maiesty doth not conceive that it can stand with instice or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to alter their Government in that particular.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And his Majesty offers to grant to every of those Lieutenants such Commissions as he hath done this Parliament to some Lords-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants by their advice; but if that power be not thought enough, but that more shall be thought fit, to be granted to them, than by the Law
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:196782:8"/>is in the Crowne it selfe, his Majesty holds it reasonable, that the same be by some Law first vested in him with power to transferre it to those persons; which he will willingly doe. And whatever that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer shall be, his Majesty desires it may be digested into an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, rather then an Ordinance; so that all his loving Subjects may thereby particularly know, both what they are to doe, and what they are to suffer for their neglect, that there may be the least latitude for his Majesties good Subjects to suffer under any Arbitrary power what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="4">4. Concerning the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> his Majesty accepted of Sir <hi>Iohn Coniers</hi> to be Lievtenant in the place of Sir <hi>Iohn Byron. February,</hi> 11.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Lastly, touching the Ordinance it selfe he refused to passe it; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the preface which he could not consent to in Iustice to his Honour, and Innocency; as also because it excluded his Maiesty from any power in the disposition, or execution of the <hi>Militia,</hi> together with them, and for a time utterly unlimited.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse, to compose this difference about the <hi>Militia</hi> (if it might be) and to comply with their desires so far as he might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violation of his Iust Rights, afterward when he sent them that Message of his purpose to goe into <hi>Ireland</hi> for suppressing the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion there (which was <hi>April.</hi> 8.) he sent also a bill for setling the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> for a yeare; and by that Bill he consented to the names they had proposed, and in the limitation of the power; and provided, that himselfe should not be able to execute any thing but by their advice; and when his Maiesty should be out of the Kingdome, the sole execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be in them,</p>
            <p>But none of all his Maiesties Answers or offers did satisfie them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing resolved from the beginning to be absolute masters of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and to dispose and execute it as they please, at all times, and upon all occasions, otherwise it could not have been sufficient and effectuall from time to time, to make good their pretended Priviledges, and power, and to back their irregular proceedings; and to compasse &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their designes. And seeing they can not obtaine it thus by Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they begin now to claime it of Right. For (<hi>March,</hi> 2. and 15.) both Houses of Parliament Resolve and Vote, <hi>That in case of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream danger, evident, and Imminent (as at this time) and upon his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:196782:8"/>Majesties refusall, they have power to order the Militia of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and the People are obliged to obey them by the Fundament all Laws of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they are confident that all these who at first stickled for them in the motion to the Lords about the <hi>Militia,</hi> will be now ready to defend them, and to maintaine these their Resolutions and Votes (if need be) even against the King himselfe.</p>
            <p>However for my part I doubt much of the Reality of this whole businesse.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whether these be Votes and Resolutions of both Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or not rather of that factious and Seditious party there; who by the insolency of Tumults have driven away divers Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both Houses, and have Captivated the votes of others, and yet would carry on their designe under the name, and by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Authority of both Houses of Parliament.</item>
               <item>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whether there be any such Imminent danger or no: either from Enemies abroad; all the neighbouring Princes being in Amity with us.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Or from the popish party at home; the papists now being weak and poore, disarmed according to Law, and to pay their forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to the Law; and being so prosecuted, that many of them left the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Or whether there is not only a pretence of dangers, that so they may the more Colourably intrust themselves in the <hi>Militia,</hi> and the people may the more readily apply themselves to them, and serve them for their safety.</p>
            <list>
               <item>3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whether setling of the <hi>Militia</hi> (as they did) absolutely in their own power, was, as is pretended, for the safeguard of His Majesties Person, and of His people (seeing it hath been imployed against both) or not rather for the safety of their owne party onely, and for the security of their designe, and that the King might have no possibility of raising the power of the Kingdome against them, and so of hindering them in the prosecution of their designe.</item>
               <item>4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whether they possessed themselves of the <hi>Militia</hi> by way of prevention, and that they might be able to defend the King and Kingdome against the designes and attempts of Papists, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Forces; or not rather by way of preparation, to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:196782:9"/>against all opposers of them, and of their designe; whether papists, or protestants; whether other Princes or their own Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And having now estated themselves in the <hi>Militia,</hi> and in the whole power of the Kingdome, see how they begin with the King himself, and how audaciously, and earnestly they pursue their designes against him, bereaved now of all meanes of offending them, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending himselfe. Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> keeps him out of <hi>Hull,</hi> by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of both Houses of Parliament. <hi>April.</hi> 23. and 28. And when upon this Traiterous Action he moved the Gentry of <hi>York</hi> for a Guard of Horse to secure his person, they voted, That his Majesty intended War against his Parliament, <hi>May</hi> 12. and 20. And they declare against the Kings Negative Vote (even in the <hi>Militia</hi>) <hi>May</hi> 26; And that they should not want duty or Modesty, if they made the highest presidents of other Parliaments their patternes <hi>(i.)</hi> if they should depose, and murder him, as other unparralleld Parliaments had done, <hi>Edward,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> both the second. Yea the Members of the House of Commons trample upon him singly: and <hi>Martin</hi> saies publiquely, and unreproved, <hi>That his Office is forfeited, and that the happinesse of this Kingdome doth not depend upon him or any of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Branches of that Stock;</hi> and <hi>Ludlow, That he was not worthy to be King of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Nor doth the designe Terminate in the person of the King, but strikes at the Regall power it selfe: And (<hi>Iunij</hi> 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>) they offer to his Majesty nineteen propositions, as the most effectuall meanes through Gods blessing of removeing the lealousies and differences betwixt them (see now the end of these politique Feares and Iealousies) and they humbly advise and petition his Maiesty (capable now as they think of any thing,)</p>
            <p>That the Lords, and others of his Maiesties privy Councell, and such great Officers and Ministers of State, either at home, or beyond the Seas, may be put from his Privy Councell, and from those Offices and Imployments; excepting such as shall be approved of by both Houses of Parliament; and that the persons to be put into their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may be approved of by both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>That the Lord High Steward of <hi>England,</hi> Lord High Constable, Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper of the Great Seale, Lord Treasurer,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:196782:9"/>Lord Privy Seale, Earle Marshall, Lord Admirall, Warden of the Cinque-portes, Chiefe Governour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Chancellor of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, Master of the Wardes, Secretaries of State, two Chiefe Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Chiefe Baron, may alwaies be chosen with the approbation of both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <list>
               <item>That the Governours of the Kings Children shall be approved of by both Houses of Parliament. And that no marriage shal be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or Treated for any those Children, without the Consent of Parliament.</item>
               <item>That His Majesty would be pleased to consent, that such a Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be made of the Church Government and Liturgy, as both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Parliament shall advise, after Consultation had with Divines.</item>
               <item>That His Majesty would rest satisfied with the course that the Lords and Commons have appointed for the <hi>Militia,</hi> untill the same shall be farther ordered by a Bill.</item>
               <item>That the Forts, and Castles of the Kingdome, may be put under the Command and Custody of such Persons as His Majesty shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point with the Approbation of his Parliament.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And being impatient that His Majesty should refuse these their modest Propositions, according to the Latitude of their desires, they resolve forthwith to put themselves into Armes, and as if the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary power of the Kingdome were not sufficient for them (to shew what they are able to doe) they will raise an Army also; both to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish whatsoever before they had Voted, and Declared, and Ordered, and Acted, and to wring and wrest from His Majesty whatsoever they had proposed: and being no better Patriots, then Subjects, they will by an Intestine Division, and Civill Warre destroy the present being of this Kingdome, rather then not to overthrow the first Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of it. And so (<hi>June</hi> 10.) they publish Propositions, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for bringing in of Mony or Plate, to maintaine Horse, Horsemen, or Armes (as is pretended) for the preservation of the publick Peace, and for the Defence of the King, and both Houses of Parliament: And they Declare, that whatsoever is brought in shall not be at all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed upon any other occasion then to maintaine the protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Kings Authority and his Person in his Royall Dignity, the free course of Iustice, the Lawes of the Laud, the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Priviledges of Parliament, against any Force that shall oppose them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:196782:10"/>
            <p>And now the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> enter againe upon the Stage, and act their parts in raising this Army, as they had done before in promoting the <hi>Militia.</hi> And to this purpose they bring in money and plate in abundance; and so doth the Disciplinarian party generally in other Cities, and Corporations, and throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that they may at length by force of Armes compleat and finish their designe; and that under the pretended Authority of both Houses of Parliament, and under the pretence of maintaining the particulars aforesaid. But the nineteen propositions sufficiently declare to the world their Intentions, and Resolutions, specially since they insisted also upon the same Propositions at the Treaty of peace. 3. <hi>February,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>Hence (<hi>Iune,</hi> 16.) his Majesty sets forth a Declaration, disavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any intention of raising or Levying war against his Parliament, shewing what a speciall number are present in Parliament; how with their skill and violence they have driven away divers Members from them; and how out of the horror of their proceedings others have withdrawne themselves from them, and that there remaines onely a malignant party who have despised his Person, and usurped his Office, and would ruine and destroy him. And by reason of the Alarmes lately given him, he thinks it necessary to put himselfe into a posture of defence, and he invites all his loving Subjects to bring in plate and money, either of guift, or upon Loans, that he may be able to raise an Army.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. For the defence, and maintenance of the Protestant Religion (es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in Worship, and Church Governement) established by law, and by vote in a full and free Convention this Parliament, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Factious and Seditious party, in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and throughout the whole Kingdome; who first overthrew the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Parliament by Tumults, and now endeavour to over throw our Religion by force of Armes, and who are countenanced by a Factious and Seditious party in the Houses, assuming to themselves the name of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. For the vindication and maintenance of the Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Parliaments</hi> against that Seditious and Tumultuous party aforesaid.</item>
               <item>3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. For the vindication and maintenance of the Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:196782:10"/>in his person and estate, against their illegall Ordinances, and Arbitrary and Tyrannicall proceedings.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And (saith the Confession of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi>) whosoever deny unto Kings and Princes their aid, counsell and comfort, whilest they travell vigilantly in the execution of their Office (as his Maiesty doth in defending and maintaining the premises, even with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his life,) we affirme that the same men deny their helpe, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and counsell to God, who by the presence of his Lieutenant doth crave it of them.</p>
            <p>Besides his Majesty raised his Army for the vindication and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his Rights taken from Him, in the Forts, and Castles, and the <hi>Militia,</hi> and his Navy, (without which He cannot discharge his Kingly Office, and protect his people) and for his negative Vote, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared against. As also for the Defence of his Crown and Life in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, after it had been declared, That they should not want duty or modesty if they followed the highest precedents of other Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>And in this respect we have a farther obligation upon us by our Oathes enjoyned by Law, which is, To defend the King to the utmost of our power, against all Conspiracies and Attempts whatsoever, which shall be made against his Majesties person, his Crown, and Dignity; and to our power to assist all jurisdictions, priviledges, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminences, and authorities, belonging to Him, or united to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Crown of this Realme.</p>
            <p>Thus have I shewed thee, Reader, the beginnings of this Warre; and therein mayst thou see the justnesse of the Kings Cause, and the necessity of his Armes; and from thence must thy Conscience be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and not from the carriage or successe of it. I have shewed thee how from the very first Reformation amongst us, there hath been a factious and seditious party, (I mean the Disciplinarians) enemies to the Church and State, how they have multiplied from time to time, and how at this time their power is encreased by reason of the popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousnesse and wealth of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and a compliance of some Members of both Houses of Parliament with them. Thou hast seen how at first in a Parliamentary way they attempted their Design of overthrowing the present Government of the Church and State; and how failing in that way, they appeared in Tumults, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:196782:11"/>the Parliament; driving away divers of the Members who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured not their ends; and captivating the Votes of others by force and violence; and how by these meanes under the name and authority of the Parliament (upon pretence of Feares and Iealousies) they pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed themselves of the power of the Kingdome, and then affronted the King in the businesse of <hi>Hull,</hi> and declared against Him, and offered Him (as a meanes of Reconciliation) propositions destructive of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; and lastly, how they took up Armes, to compleat and finish their Designe; whereupon his Majesty was necessitated to arme Himself also, for defence of Himselfe and of the Parliament, and of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and of our Religion.</p>
            <p>And be thou assured, that they who could not carry their businesse in a full and free Convention of Parliament, will never be able to prevaile upon a free Debate and Treaty, and so they will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it in a Treaty; but what they begun by Tumults, they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine and establish by the Sword; so the differences are irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable, and the course of Warre unalterable, and the destruction of thy poore Countrey inevitable. Rowse up therefore thy selfe for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the peace of thy Countrey; and have publique thoughts in thee of supporting the frame of this tottering Church and State, rather than of saving thy selfe, and thine, (knowing also that thy private can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be safe so long as the publike is in danger:) and apply thy selfe forthwith to his Majesties service, and be zealous and industrious in it; and resolve under his Majesty to live and die a loyall Subject to thy Soveraigne, a faithfull Servant of the Parliament, a true <hi>English</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant, and a free-borne <hi>English-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And the glorious Maiesty of the our Lord God be upon us, prosper thou the worke of our hands upon us, O prosper thou our handy workes.</q>
            <p>And, Reader, for thy better information, and through satisfaction concerning this present Warre, I shall now lay down before thee the Grounds of my own resolution against the Warre on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments side, in point of Conscience.</p>
            <q>Whatsoever is not of faith, is sin. Rom. <hi>14.23. (i.) saith Master</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Whatsoever a man doth, his Conscience reluctating, or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or erring, is sin in the party so doing it.</q>
            <p>In this case</p>
            <p n="1">1. My Conscience doubteth whether this be a free Parliament; or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:196782:11"/>no; <hi>(i.)</hi> whether the Members of both Houses had their freedome of Vote in Parliament, or whether it was not taken away by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, Separatists, and others, in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the present Government of the Church and State; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorting in great multitudes to <hi>Westminster</hi> with swords and clubs, (and sent for to) when any thing was likely to be carried in the Houses against their party, and contrary to their Designe.</p>
            <p>I doubt also whether his Majesty had his freedome, or his safety; those tumultuous people, as they passed through the streets, using ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny desperate &amp; seditious speeches, That the King was the Traitor, That the young Prince would governe better, That it is not fit the King should live. Yea in the height of their rage, as they returned from <hi>Westminster,</hi> they made a stand at <hi>Whitehall</hi> Gate, (as they were bid to do) saying, That they will have no more Porters Lodge, but would speak with the King when they pleased.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The King and Members not having freedome and safety. I doubt whether this be a Parliament or no. For what is a Parliament but a Carcase, when the freedome thereof is suppressed? saith Master <hi>Pym,</hi> in his Speech of <hi>The Discovery of the great Plot.</hi> And say the Lords and Commons at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in their late Declaration, for want of freedome of Vote, the power of Parliament is suspended; and there can be no Parliamentary Action or Authority untill it be restored and secured. And in the interim, the Members at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> sit, not in a politique, but a naturall capacity onely, and so have no power or authority to act or command any thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If this were a full and free Convention of Parliament, I doubt whether the two Houses of Parliament have Authority to take up Armes against the King, be it for preservation of Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for,</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1. The Members of both Houses are Subjects, (and so acknowledge themselves in their petitions to his Majesty) and I doubt, whether even in these cases Subjects may take up Armes against their Soveraigne. The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> delivered in the Bookes of Homilies, is clearly against it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Again, the Subjects of the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> diffusively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered cannot take up Armes against the King, and how then can their Representatives assembled in Parliament, seeing they have no power but what the people at large have given them.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:196782:12"/>
            <list>
               <item n="2">2. I have not read or heard of any known Law warranting them thus to take up Armes; and I doubt whether they may do it (as is pretended) by the Fundamentall Lawes of the Land. For if the thus preserving of Religion and Liberty (against the King, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to alter the one, or destroy the other) were committed to the Houses of Parliament by the Constitution of the Kingdome, doubtlesse it would never have given power to the King of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and dissolving Parliaments at pleasure; for so that meanes of preservation is made uncertain, yea it becomes certainly none at all; seeing it cannot be conceived, but the King in that case would either not call, or presently dissolve the Parliament, if He saw they would arme themselves against Him. Yea, rather I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the King hath power to call and dissolve Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the Constitution of the Kingdome, that so He may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all such proceedings, which would otherwise from time to time embroile the Kingdome in Civill Warre.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So these Armes being not warranted by any Law, all their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Commands, in order to this Warre, are one onely perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and of their own private wills, not legall and judiciall; and so may be resisted by their own exposition of the place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>Yea, this pretended legall power of Subjects taking up Armes against their Soveraigne, is against the very Fundamentals of policy, and tends to the destruction of policies: for in every constituted Kingdome and Common-wealth there is but one Sword, and that committed to the Supreme Magistrate; and if the people also were armed with another Sword, how upon all occasions (reall and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as at this day) would there be continuall clashing between them, and intestine Divisions, and Civill Warres, than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more pernicious and destructive to a Common-wealth, no not Tyranny it selfe.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse in this case we are not left remedilesse, even by the constitution of the Kingdome. For whereas it is said, The King can do no wrong; and what is so done, is said ever to be done by evill Counsellours and Instruments; by the Fundamentals of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the House of Commons have power to indite and prosecute, and the House of Lords to iudge and censure, such Counsellours and Instruments, though fled beyond the Seas; and so to vindicate and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:196782:12"/>our Liberties: and how this might have been done effectually at this time in a Parliamentary way, against all remaining in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, you shall see in the resolution of the following Doubt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Warre being the last Remedy, and not to be undertaken but in case of extreme necessity, I doubt of the necessity of this present Warre.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1. In respect of the preservation of the Protestant Religion against Popery; his Majesty by his Message <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. pressing them speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and seriously to consider of all things necessary for the security of the true Religion now professed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> (with due consideration of weak consciences, in point of Ceremony.) And by that other Message <hi>Febr.</hi> 14. declaring his resolution to proceed strictly against Papists, and to banish out of the Kingdome all <hi>Romish</hi> Priests; and setting forth a Proclamation for putting all Lawes in execution against Papists without favour or connivance, <hi>March</hi> 16 Also in his Answer to the Propositions <hi>June</hi> 2, offering to joyne with the Houses in a speciall Act against Priests and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits disturbing the State, and against Papists cluding the Lawes by Trust; and for the Education of the Children of Papists by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants in the Protestant Religion (which offer his Majesty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in his Message to the Lords and Commons for a Treaty of Peace, <hi>April</hi> 12. 1643.) And by these meanes Popery would have been suppressed for the present, and in time to come might have been rooted out; in a Legall and Parliamentary way.</item>
               <item n="2">2. In respect of the preservation of the Liberty of the Subject; which after it had been asserted by severall Acts this Parliament, his Majesty by the said Message <hi>Ian.</hi> 20. advised them farther to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to themselves, if it were needfull. And had there been any Invasion of our Liberties, (as who durst invade them? the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament sitting as long as they please, by the Act of Continuation, which secures unto them a full operation of all Remedies in this kinde, according to their own confession in the Remonstrance, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 15) I say, had any one presumed to invade out Liberties, the <hi>Militia</hi> being also setled (as it might have been) by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in the hands of such Lieutenants as they did confide in, which his Majesty offered to do, not excluding Himselfe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Execution of it, there would have been a sure
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:196782:13"/>meanes of bringing to condigne punishment the offenders in that kinde; because the Houses might in such a case have caused that Act to be put in Execution, in order to the preservation of our Liberty, and of Religion too, if needfull; and of their power and priviledge of calling in, and proceeding against Delinquents also, as they have power upon occasion to put any Law in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. But they would not be satisfied with that offer of the Kings for setling the <hi>Militia</hi> in the ordinary way, because it could not agree with their ends, which were extraordinary: nor could they afterward so well have put the <hi>Militia</hi> (as they did) in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against Him, unlesse at first they had ordered it to be executed without Him.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="5">5. These Armes taken up at first onely Defensively (as was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) are used also offensively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To overthrow our Religion by Law established, in Doctrine, Worship, Government, and Discipline; which is also contrary to the profession they made in their Orders and Propositions for bringing in Money and Place, <hi>Iune</hi> 10. For therein they declare, that whatsoever is brought in shall not at all be imployed upon any other occasion than to maintain the Protestant Religion, the Lawes of the Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that must doubtlesse be the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion established by the Lawes of the Land.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To overthrow the Kings Legall Prerogative, and Supremacy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Ecclesiasticall matters, by abolishing of Episcopacy, and setting up the Presbytery; for whereas the Bishops (the chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church under his Majesty) have their nomination from the King, and there is a finall Appeale from them to the King, the Presbyterian Discipline doth admit of neither, but will be in both respects independent to Him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Civill matters, by taking from Him the nomination of the great Officers of State, and of the Lord Admirall, and of the Warden of the Cinque Ports, and the Disposition of the Forts and Castles, and of the <hi>Militia, &amp;c.</hi> and by setling the chiefe power in all these things for ever in the Parliament: and this is also contrary to the profession they made in their Propositions and Orders, <hi>Iune</hi> 10. for therein they declare, That whatsoever is brought in shal not at all be imployed upon any other occasion than to maintain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:196782:13"/>the Kings Authority, and his Person in his Royall Dignity.</p>
            <p>Yea, these Armes are used to overthrow the very first Constitution of the Kingdome; by endeavouring to bring in the Presbytery in the Church, and Aristocracy and Democracy in the Common-wealth, and of a Soveraigne to make this a meere Titular Monarchy. And this doubtlesse was the Designe from the Beginning; for what is last in execution is ever first in intention, as <hi>è contra;</hi> and in the Act for the Continuation of this Parliament, they laid their foundation for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting it; and afterward they prosecuted it from time to time: first by the Protestation, then by Sir <hi>Arthur Hasterigges</hi> Bill, and by their Remonstrance, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 15. and by imploying seditious Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and by licencing seditious Pamphlets, and by raising and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing Tumults, by protecting the Lord <hi>Kymbolton</hi> and the Five Members, by putting the Bishops out of the House of Lords, by wresting the <hi>Militia</hi> from the King, by scruing and detaining from Him his Magazine at <hi>Hull,</hi> by their Declarations, that especially <hi>May</hi> 26. by the tender of the nineteen Propositions; and lastly, by their taking up Armes; yea, by their malitious and perverse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions and applications, they made all occurrents past and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, in Church and State, subservient to this their Designe.</p>
            <p>Lastly, these Armes are used to overthrow the very Constitution of Parliament, and to compell the Kings Vote and consent to those things, against Himselfe, against the Church, and therein against his Oath which He took at his Coronation to defend the Bishops and their Churches.</p>
            <p>And in this fifth and last respect, there is in me a reluctancy of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science against this Warre on the Parliaments side.</p>
            <p>And you, who out of an erroneous Conscience have engaged your selves in this Warre, on the Parliaments part against the King, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished from henceforth to desist, and to repent; for as much as you may plainly see, that since the Tumults begun this was not a free Parliament, and so for the time no Parliament at all, in respect of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or authority; and if it were a full and free Convention of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, yet they have no power to take up Armes against the King, be it for preservation of Religion and Liberty; and at this time there was no necessity of taking up Armes in these respects; yea, and the Armes taken up are used offensively, and imployed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:196782:14"/>against the King, the Law, and Religion; to overthrow the Religion by Law established, and to devest the King of his just legall Prerogative, and so to overthrow the Fundamentall Constitution of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now whosoever go about to overthrow Policies long since esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished, are enemies to mankinde, and fight against God's expressed will, saith the Confession of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>O my Soule, come not thou into their secret,</q>
               <bibl>Gen. 49.6.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>